<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Gentoolink Web Services Inc. - Blog</title><link href="https://gentoolink.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://gentoolink.com/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://gentoolink.com/</id><updated>2022-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Using Python to create static website</title><link href="https://gentoolink.com/static-website-generation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ken McGonigal</name></author><id>tag:gentoolink.com,2022-10-19:/static-website-generation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is entire website: gentoolink.com is made from html, javascript and css using a static website generator.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;This website is not WordPress!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is entire website: gentoolink.com is made from html, javascript and css using a static website generator. The static generator uses the Python computer programming language to generate a website. In this case I used the Pelican website generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This enables the use of a combination of markdown, html, bootstrap css to custom build the website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of website is Google friendly which means it is optimized for search engines like Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am writing this blog post in Markdown. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;No Database&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website does not use a database. It has dynamic content without the use of PHP. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to bring this up because WordPress is overused in my opinion. The popularity of WordPress has led to security issues not because WordPress is a bad product; but due to its popularity has become a target of hackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a custom coded website is better. This leaves only the security of the server it is hosted on. It does not eliminate all security issues, but elimates a popular one. WordPress also has constant updates. A static site is only updated when you change or update the content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This in turn leads to lower costs. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Why use a static website instead of WordPress?</title><link href="https://gentoolink.com/why-use-static-websites.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-31T18:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-10T20:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ken McGonigal</name></author><id>tag:gentoolink.com,2019-01-31:/why-use-static-websites.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The reasons to use a static website.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Why use a static website? What is a static website?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days it is quite simple to automatically use WordPress or some
other content management system (CMS). The question is what kind of
business are you in? Does your business need a CMS like WordPress?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most small businesses may only need a static website to list thier
business on the internet. Will you be using your website to collect data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the difference between a static website and a CMS or WordPress?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Static:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed in incredibly fast!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The content stays the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More secure as there is no database to hack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CMS:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;content is dynamic and changes regularily&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not as fast due to server and database calls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can be updated by users with different security levels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are your business needs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will your business website change much after it is created? If the answer is
no then a static website is preferred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will your business website need frequent (daily or weekly) updates and changes?
Then  a CMS like WordPress makes more sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is your website needs to be improving your business by
increasing leads and revenue. So your website needs to be as unique as your and
your business are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't settle for just a Facebook page or a do-it-yourself website building service.
Get it done right with a professional so you have more time to work on what you are
good at--your busines!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Do you need personal cloud space?</title><link href="https://gentoolink.com/cloud-space.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-09T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-10-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ken McGonigal</name></author><id>tag:gentoolink.com,2018-12-09:/cloud-space.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you need personal cloud space? How about private cloud space? Not Dropbox.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The Revolution of the cloud has started&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure by now in 2018 you have heard of the cloud. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five Reasons to own and control your cloud:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgrade-ability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few ways you can own your own cloud space. No  I am not talking about iCloud or Dropbox. Both iCloud and Dropbox require a paid subscription to really use them for all your data syncing across devices.  Although these services are superb; if you like your privacy you may want to reconsider where you store your personal files. Remember when services are free…you are the product. You can also control where your files are stored and have more space for lower cost per gigabyte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few ways you can accomplish owning your cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purchase hardware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purchase hosting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud hosting software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have setup my own cloud which includes full encryption via ssl and all the files on the server are encrypted as well. So even if someone were to gain physical or logical access to the server they would not be able to read the files. Nextcloud enables me to use a combination of data storage. I have my cloud hosted from a VPS and also storing files to AWS S3. All files are encrypted so it is secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how can you get started you ask? If you are tech savvy you could buy your own hardware like a small NAS server with cloud software and host it from your home or office. Or you could purchase a Virtual Private Server (VPS) from a hosting provider like Amazon, Hostgator or Open Stack etc… Then use Nextcloud to host your cloud. You will need a domain and ssl certificate to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of using a service like Amazon Web Services is the uptime is almost 100%. If you have a server in your home or office the power source could be interrupted and your cloud will be down as well. Also you have to think about physical security. If you suffered a home break in or office break in you could loose your precious data. Large hosting companies usually have physical security in their data centers. And you can access and manage a VPS or EC2 instance just as easy as if the computer was in your home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you purchase hardware it will eventually need an upgrade. While a VPS has a yearly cost you don’t need to worry about replacing hardware when it breaks down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are not tech savvy; but still would like your own cloud then hiring a consultant would be the best option.&lt;/strong&gt;
 If you have any suggestions or questions leave a comment below. I am also available for hire if you would like an Nextcloud installation done for you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>What you need when building a website</title><link href="https://gentoolink.com/website-needs.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-08T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-08T08:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ken McGonigal</name></author><id>tag:gentoolink.com,2018-12-08:/website-needs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What do you need when building a website&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are a few items you need to buy when building a website.  The very first thing you need to buy is a domain name. Without a domain name your website will not be visible on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choose a Domain Name&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several vendors who can sell you a domain name. I am recommending Namecheap.com as this is the vendor I deal with on a regular basis. You also have to check if your domain name is available. If you make your domain name unique to your business or blog then it should be available. You can also consider buying a top level domain other than .COM. There are several new TLD to choose from now. For example if your business is photography you can buy yourbusiness.photography. This is changing the traditional internet TLD names like .com etc...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choose a Hosting Provider&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need a hosting package. Hosting is where the actual website files live. This place is a computer called a server. These servers are located in very large data centers owned by large companies. I use Hostgator.com where I rent a VPS to host websites for my clients. I also host my own websites on the same server. There are many hosting companies out there to choose from. mainflyerbanner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do I need a SSL Certificate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Let's Encrypt" src="https://letsencrypt.org/images/letsencrypt-logo-horizontal.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also need to buy an SSL certificate. You can purchase one depending on
your needs. Gentoolink Web Services supplies free Let's Encrypt services for 
your domain when hosted with us. If your website requires users to login or buy things from a store then you will need to secure it with a SSL certificate. A SSL certificate is a set of keys to enable encryption between computers communicating on the internet. SSL certificates can vary in price depending on what you need it for. Most people just can buy a $20 SSL certificate without worries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do I need a web developer?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need a web developer. If you are not a tech savvy person then you need to hire someone. The price varies on what type of website you want or need. If you just need a brochure type of website it is usually less labor intensive. If you require an online store with ways for customers to shop and buy from your website this costs considerably more. A brochure type website is usually about five pages with pictures. An E-commerce website is usually allot larger. You definitely need to hire someone for  an E-commerce website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I use a free website for my business? Well that depends on you and your specific needs and
business problems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe the best answer for this question is...don't you want a great website? Don't you want a website which doesn't look like everyone else's free website? Free website builders are limited in features. The main feature I would like to mention is the ability to have user logins and a private website which is commonly called  a "Walled Garden".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should also setup a page on Instagram, Pinterest, Twitter and Facebook. These powerful social media platforms will give your website exposure. If you are not sure how to do this you can always ask your website developer how to to this.  The power of social media and its viral qualities cannot be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your new website will also need to be optimized for the search engines to find it. If you have any questions or comments feel free to use the contact page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contact me through my social media channels!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry></feed>